<tool id="ramid" name="ramid" version="0.1.0">
<stdio>
<exit_code range="1:" />
</stdio>
<description>Evaluates the peaks of mass isotopomer distribution (MID), making them ready for correction for natural isotope occurrence.</description>
<command><![CDATA[
runRamid.R -i "$inputExchange" -o "$outputExchange" -z "$zipped_data"
]]></command>
<inputs>
	<param type="data" name="inputExchange" format="csv" />
	<param type="data" name="zipped_data" format="zip" />
</inputs>
<outputs>
    <data name="outputExchange" format="csv" label="Corrected isotopologues file"/>
</outputs>
<help>
==============
RaMID
==============

Version: 1.0

-----------------
Short description
-----------------

R-program to read CDF files, created by mass spectrometer, and evaluate the mass spectra of 13C-labeled metabolites

-----------
Description
-----------

RaMID is a computer program designed to read the machine-generated files saved in netCDF format containing registered time course of m/z chromatograms. It evaluates the peaks of mass isotopomer distribution (MID) making them ready for further correction for natural isotope occurrence. To create the docker image the github repository "https://github.com/seliv55/RaMID" is used.

------------
Key features
------------

- Primary processing of 13C mass isotopomer data obtained with GCMS

-------------
Functionality
-------------

- Preprocessing of raw data
- Initiation of workflows

----------
Approaches
----------

- Isotopic Labeling Analysis / 13C

---------------------
Instrument Data Types
---------------------

- MS

-------------
Data Analysis
-------------

RaMID reads the CDF files presented in the working directory, and then separates the time courses for selected m/z peaks corresponding to specific mass isotopomers; corrects baseline for each selected mz; choses the time points where the distribution of peaks is less contaminated by other compounds and thus is the most representative of the real analyzed distribution of mass isotopomers; evaluates this distribution, and saves it in files readable by MIDcor, a program, which performs the next step of analysis, i.e. correction of the RaMID spectra for natural isotope occurrence, which is necessary to perform a fluxomic analysis. Correction for H+ loss produced by electron impact, natural occurring isotopes, and peaks overlapping.

</help>
</tool>
