<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--Proposed Tool Section: [File Handling]-->
<tool id="rnmr1d" name="rnmr1d" version="0.4">
  <requirements>
    <container type="docker">container-registry.phenomenal-h2020.eu/phnmnl/rnmr1d</container>
  </requirements>
  <description>Preprocessing RAW NMR data with macro-commands.</description>
  <command><![CDATA[
    mkdir -p /data/input;
    mkdir -p /data/output;
    /opt/rnmr1d/exec/Rnmr1D --zip $infile --proccmd $macrofile --outnorm PQN --cpu 8 --outdir /data/output 2>&1;
    cat /data/output/data_matrix.txt > $outfile;
  ]]>
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="infile" type="data" format="no_unzip.zip" optional="False" label="Zipped nmrML data file collection" help="nmrML files inside a zip file, all files at the root level." />
    <param name="macrofile" type="data" format="txt" optional="False" label="Macro-Command file" />
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data name="outfile" type="data" format="txt" label="NMR data matrix" />
  </outputs>
<help><![CDATA[
Pre-process RAW NMR data with macro-commands using Rnmr1D.

.. class::infomark

**Author**  
Kristian Peters (IPB-Halle) wrote this wrapper, Reza Salek (EMBL-EBI) feedback and testing it. The Rnmr1D NMR data processing tool in "R" was written by Daneil Jacob (INRA) (see below)

----------------------------------------------------------------------------------

.. class:: infomark

**Tool**

A Java program to convert vendor NMR RAW data to open souece nmrML XML format


----------------------------------------------------------------------------------

.. class:: infomark

**Tool updates**

See the **NEWS** section at the bottom of this page

----------------------------------------------------------------------------------

.. class:: infomark

================================================================================
**Rnmr1D**: Processing nmrML or verndor NMR data
================================================================================

-----------
Description
-----------

Rnmr1D is the main module from the NMRProcFlow web application (http://nmrprocflow.org) develpped by Daniel Jacob (INRA), for 1D NMR spectra data processing.
Rnmr1D allows users to process their NMR spectra using set of macro-command sequence. Outside NMRProcFlow Rnmr1D become a CLI application allowing users to replay the macro-command sequence generated within NMRProcFlow. Moreover, without using NMRProcFlow, this module can also be used to replace any 'home-made script' by a macro-command sequence. See Parameters for details. 

.. class:: infomark

**References**

| Jacob D, Deborde C, Lefebvre M, Maucourt M, Moing A. NMRProcFlow: a graphical and interactive tool dedicated to 1D spectra processing for NMR-based metabolomics. Metabolomics. 2017;13(4):36. doi:10.1007/s11306-017-1178-y.

---------------------------------------------------

-----------------
Workflow position
-----------------

Right after the nmrMLConv in a workflow or Galaxy nmrML/Vedor RAW NMR data

.. image:: rnmr1d.png
    :height: 425
    :width: 392

-----------
Input files
-----------

Galaxy dataset nmrML or Vendor file format. Data input could be Zipped (preferred) or as individual files

----------
Parameters
----------
Use the macro editor for parameters, you need the have the correct Macro parameters as input for data processing (updated coming soon, currently as input .txt script file)

------------
Output files
------------

Output:
 | NMR data matrix with aligned values (CSV format)
 | Bucket file
 | Spectra file


---------------------------------------------------

.. class:: infomark

**License**
Copyright (C) 2017 Daniel Jacob - INRA

This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.


----
NEWS
----

More updates soonocessing dor
 ]]></help>
</tool>
