<tool id="midcor" name="midcor" version="0.1.0">
<requirements>
    <!-- Container based dependency handling -->
    <container type="docker">container-registry.phenomenal-h2020.eu/phnmnl/midcor:v1.0_cv1.0.40</container>
</requirements> 	
<stdio>
<exit_code range="1:" />
</stdio>
<description>corrects 13C mass isotopomers spectra of metabolites for natural occurring isotopes and peaks overlapping.</description>
<command><![CDATA[
runMidcor.R -i "$input1" -o "$output1"
]]></command>
<inputs>
<param type="data" name="input1" format="csv" />
</inputs>
<outputs>
    <data name="output1" format="csv" label="Corrected isotopologues file"/>
</outputs>
<help><![CDATA[
The presented here computational support for 13C tracer-based analysis of intracellular metabolic fluxes consists of several subsequent steps. They are the extraction of necessary data from raw mass spectrometer recording for 13C labeled metabolites, provided in a series of files of the netCDF format; their correction for the natural isotope enrichment and possible overlapping of mass spectra; simulation of the corrected data using a kinetic model of underlying metabolic processes.

*MIDcor* is an R program that corrects the raw mass spectra of artificially 13C labeled metabolites. These spectra are extracted at the previous step of this workflow with the program RaMID from netCDF files generated by a Gas Cromatography / Mass Spectrometry (GCMS) machine. In this way it supports the second step of analysis of 13C tracer distribution in metabolites. It takes the raw mass spectra saved by RaMID in the file exchangeable with database Metabolights and correct them for natural isotopes abundance and possible peaks overlapping as described in [1].

The “R” code of MIDcor together with a description of its using (README.md) and some examples are freely available from https://github.com/seliv55/midcor.  In one of the provided examples, the workflow starts from a set of CDF files containing the data recording for three cell types. MIDcor receives this information processed altogether. To facilitate the next step, simulation of labeling and metabolic fluxes, MIDcor separates the resulted corrected distributions for each type of cells. It adds the corrected data into the last column of the input exchange file, keeping the same format.

[1] Selivanov VA, Benito A, Miranda A, Aguilar E, Polat IH, Centelles JJ, Jayaraman A, Lee PW, Marin S, Cascante M. MIDcor, an R-program for deciphering mass interferences in mass spectra of metabolites enriched in stable isotopes. BMC Bioinformatics. 2017 18 : 88
	]]></help>
</tool>
